stage.
It was on May the 1st that the two came
back at last to the brink of the valley of Rivendell, where stood the last or
the first homely house. Again it was evening. Their polies were tired,
especially the one that carried the baggage, and they all felt in need of
rest. As they rode down the steep path, Bilbo heard the elves still singing in
the trees, as if they had not stopped since he left. And as soon as the riders
came down into the lower glades of the wood, they burst into a song of much the
same kind as before. This is something like it. The dragon is withered. His
bones are now crumbled. His armor is shivered. His splendor is humbled.
Though sword shall be rusted, and throne and crown perish with strength that men
trusted, and wealth that they cherish.
Here grass is still growing, and leaves are yet swinging. The white water
flowing and elves are yet singing. Come Tralanali, come back to the valley. The stars are
far brighter than gems without measure.
The moon is far wider than silver and treasure. The fire is more shining on
hearth in the glaming than gold won by mining. So why go roaming? Oh tr
come back to the valley. Oh where are you going so late in returning? The
river is flowing the stars are all burning.
Oh wither so laden so sad and so dreary here elf and elf maiden now welcome the
weary with trali come back to the valley trali fali.
Then the elves of the valley came out and greeted them and led them across the
water to the house of Eland. There a warm welcome was made them, and there
were many eager ears that evening to hear the tale of their adventures.
Gandalf it was who spoke, for Bilbo was falling quiet and drowsy. Most of the
tale he knew, for he had been in it, and had himself told much of it to the
wizard on their homewood way or in the house of Bejorn.
But every now and again he would open one eye and listen when a part of the
story which he did not yet know came in.
It was in this way that he learned where Gandalf had been to, for he overheard
the words of the wizard to Eland. It appeared that Gandalf had been to a
great council of the white wizards, masters of lore and good magic, and that
they had at last driven the necromancer from his dark hold in the south of Murkwood.
He long now, Gandalf was saying, the forest will grow somewhat more
wholesome. The north will be freed from that horror for many long years. I hope
yet I wish he were banished from the world. It would be well indeed, said
Arand, but I fear that will not come about in this age of the world or for
many after. When the tale of their journeyings was told, there were other
tales, and yet more tales. Tales of long ago, and tales of new things, and tales
of no time at all, till Bilbo's head fell forward on his chest, and he snored
comfortably in a corner. He woke to find himself in a white bed, and the moon
shining through an open window. Below it, many elves were singing loud and
clear on the banks of the stream.
Sing all ye joyful. Now sing allto together. The winds in the treetop, the
winds in the heather, the stars are in blossom, the moon is in flower, and
bright are the windows of night in her tower. Dance, oh ye joyful, now dance
allto together. Soft is the grass, and let foot be like feather. The river is
silver, the shadows are fleeting. Mary is May time, and Mary our meeting. Sing
we now softly, and dreams let us weave him. Wind him in slumber, and there let
us leave him. The wanderer sleepeth, now soft be his pillow. Nalaby, alder in
willow. Sigh, no more pine, till the wind of the mourn. Foul moon, dark be
the land. Hush, hush, oak, ash, and thorn. Hushed be your water till dawn is at hand.
Well, merry people, said Bilbo, looking out. What time by the moon is this? Your
lullabi would waken a drunken goblin, yet I thank you. And your snores would
waken a stone dragon, yet we thank you.
They answered with laughter. It is drying towards dawn, and you have slept
now since the night's beginning.
Tomorrow perhaps you will be cured of weariness.
A little sleep does a great cure in the house of Eland, said he, but I will take
all the cure I can get. A second good night, fair friends. And with that he
went back to bed and slept till late morning. Weariness fell from him soon in
that house, and he had many a merry jest and dance early and late with the elves
of the valley. Yet even that place could not long delay him now, and he thought
always of his own home. After a week, therefore, he said farewell to Eland,
and giving him such small gifts as he would accept, he rode away with Gandalf.
Even as they left the valley, the sky darkened in the west before them, and
wind and rain came up to meet them.
"Merry is May time," said Bilbo, as the rain beat into his face. "But our back
is to legends, and we are coming home. I suppose this is the first taste of it."
There is a long road yet, said Gandalf.
But it is the last road, said Bilbo.
They came to the river that marked the very edge of the borderland of the wild,
and to the ford beneath the steep bank, which you may remember. The water was
swollen both with the melting of the snows at the approach of summer and with
the day long rain. But they crossed with some difficulty and pressed forward as
evening fell on the last stage of their journey. This was much as it had been
before, except that the company was smaller and more silent. Also this time
there were no trolls. At each point on the road, Bilbo recalled the happenings
and the words of a year ago. It seemed to him more like Teno, that of course he
quickly noted the place where the pony had fallen in the river, and they had
turned aside for their nasty adventure with Tom and Bert and Bill. Not far from
the road they found the gold of the trolls, which they had buried, still hidden and untouched.
I have enough to last me my time, said Bilbo, when they had dug it up. You had
better take this, Gandalf. I dare say you can find a use for it. Indeed, I
can," said the wizard. "But share and share alike. Ye may find you have more
needs than you expect." So they put the gold in bags and slung them on the
ponies, who were not at all pleased about it. After that their going was
slower, for most of the time they walked, but the land was green, and
there was much grass through which the hobbit strolled along contentedly.
He mocked his face with a red silk handkerchief. No, not a single one of
his own had survived. He had borrowed this one from Elron for now June had
brought summer, and the weather was bright and hot again. As all things come
to an end, even this story, a day came at last, when they were inside of the
country where Bilbo had been born and bred, where the shapes of the land and
of the trees were as well known to him as his hands and toes.
coming to arise, he could see his own hill in the distance, and he stopped
suddenly and said, "Roads go ever on, over rock and under tree, by caves where
never sun has shown, by streams that never find the sea. Over snow by winter
sewn, and through the merry flowers of June, over grass and over stone, and
under mountains in the moon.
Roads go ever on under cloud and under star. Yet feet that wandering have gone.
Turn at last to home a fire. Eyes that fire and sword have seen and horror in
the halls of stone. Look at last on meadows green and trees and hills they
long have known. Gandalf looked at him.
My dear Bilbo, he said, something is the matter with you. You are not the hobbit
that you were. And so they crossed the bridge and passed the mill by the river
and came right back to Bilbo's own door.
"Bless me, what's going on?" he cried.
There was a great commotion, and people of all sorts, respectable and
unrespectable, were thick round the door, and many were going in and out,
not even wiping their feet on the mat, as Bilbo noticed with annoyance.
If he was surprised, they were more surprised still. He had arrived back in
the middle of an auction.
There was a large notice in black and red hung on the gate stating that on
June the 22nd Messer's Grub, Grub and Burroughs would sell by auction the
effects of the late Bilbo Baggins Esquire of Bag End Underh Hill Hobbiton.
Sale to commence at 10:00 sharp. It was now nearly lunchtime, and most of the
things had already been sold for various prices from next to nothing to old
songs, as is not unusual at auctions.
Bilbo's cousins, the Sackville Baggins, were in fact busy measuring his rooms to
see if their own furniture would fit. In short, Bilbo was presumed dead, and not
everybody that said so was sorry to find the presumption wrong. The return of Mr.
Bill Boaggins created quite a disturbance both under the hill and over
the hill and across the water. It was a great deal more than a 9 days wonder.
The legal bother indeed lasted for years. It was quite a long time before
Mr. Baggins was in fact admitted to be alive again. The people who had got
specially good bargains at the sale took a deal of convincing, and in the end, to
save time, Bilbo had to buy back quite a lot of his own furniture. Many of his
silver spoons mysteriously disappeared and were never accounted for.
Personally, he suspected the sackfilled Bagginses. On their side, they never
admitted that the returned Baggins was genuine, and they were not on friendly
terms with Bilbo ever after. They really had wanted to live in his nice hobbit
hole so very much. Indeed, Bilbo found he had lost more than spoons, he had
lost his reputation. It is true that forever after he remained an elf friend
and had the honor of dwarves, wizards, and all such folk as ever passed that
way, but he was no longer quite respectable. He was in fact held by all
the hobbits of the neighborhood to be queer, except by his nephews and nieces
on the to side, but even they were not encouraged in their friendship by their elders.
I am sorry to say he did not mind. He was quite content, and the sound of the
kettle on his hearth was ever after more musical than it had been, even in the
quiet days before the unexpected party.
His sword he hung over the mantelpiece.
His coat of mail was arranged on a stand in the hall until he lent it to a
museum. His gold and silver was largely spent in presents, both useful and
extravagant, which to a certain extent accounts for the affection of his
nephews and his nieces. His magic ring he kept a great secret, for he chiefly
used it when unpleasant callers came. He took to writing poetry and visiting the
elves, and though many shook their heads and touched their foreheads, and said,
"Poor old Baggins!" And though few believed any of his tales, he remained
very happy to the end of his days, and those were extraordinarily long. One
autumn evening, some years afterwards, Bilbo was sitting in his study, writing
his memoirs, he thought of calling them there and back again a hobbit's holiday.
When there was a ring at the door, it was Gandalf and a dwarf, and the dwarf
was actually Balon.
Come in, come in, said Bilbo, and soon they were settled in chairs by the fire.
If Balin noticed that Mr. Baggin's waist coat was more extensive and had real
gold buttons, Bilbo also noticed that Balin's beard was several inches longer,
and his jeweled belt was of great magnificence.
They fell to talking of their times together, of course, and Bilbo asked how
things were going in the lands of the mountain. It seemed they were going very
well. Bard had rebuilt the town in Dale, and men had gathered to him from the
lake, and from south and west, and all the valley had become tilled again, and
rich, and the desolation was now filled with birds, and blossoms in spring and
fruit, and feasting in autumn. And Lake Town was refounded, and was more
prosperous than ever, and much wealth went up and down the running river. And
there was friendship in those pites between elves and dwarves and men. The
old master had come to a bad end. Bard had given him much gold for the help of
the lake people, but being of the kind that easily catches such disease, he
fell under the dragon sickness, and took most of the gold and fled with it, and
died of starvation in the waste, deserted by his companions.
The new master is of wiser kind, said Balin, and very popular, for of course
he gets most of the credit for the present prosperity. They are making
songs which say that in his day the rivers run with gold. Then the
prophecies of the old songs have turned out to be true after a fashion, said Bilbo.
Of course, said Gandalf, and why should not they prove true? Surely you don't
disbelieve the prophecies because you had a hand in bringing them about
yourself. You don't really suppose, do you, that all your adventures and
escapes were managed by mere luck, just for your sole benefit? You are a very
fine person, Mr. Bakans, and I am very fond of you, but you are only quite a
little fellow in a wide world after all.
Thank goodness, said Bilbo, laughing and